"Acid Reflux Medicine
May Cause Osteoporosis"
Nearly one in five adults
in the world
may have osteoporosis.
That's hundreds of millions
of people.
The word "osteoporosis"
literally means "porous bone."
Now, most of our bone
is actually porous
to begin with.
This is what normal bone
looks like inside,
but this is osteoporosis.
Bone mineral density
is considered to be
the standard measure for
the diagnosis of osteoporosis.
Although the bone mineral
density cut-off
for an osteoporosis diagnosis
is kind of arbitrary,
using the standard definition,
osteoporosis may affect
about 1 in 10 women by age 60,
2 in 10 by age 70,
4 in 10 by age 80,
and 6 or 7 out of 10 by age 90.
Osteoporosis
is typically thought of
as a disease in women,
but one third of hip fractures
occur in men.
The lifetime risk
for osteoporotic fractures
for 50-year-old
white women and men
are 40 percent and 13 percent,
respectively.
The good news is that
osteoporosis need not occur.
Based on a study of the largest
twin registry in the world,
less than 30 percent
of osteoporotic fracture risk
is heritable,
leading the researchers
to conclude,
"Prevention of fractures
[even] in the oldest elderly
should focus on
lifestyle interventions."
This is consistent with
the enormous variation
of hip fracture rates
around the world,
with the incidence
of hip fracture varying 10-fold,
or even 100-fold
between countries,
suggesting that
excessive bone loss
is not just an inevitable
consequence of aging.
The United States
Preventive Services Task Force,
an independent scientific panel
that sets evidence-based,
clinical prevention guidelines,
recommends
osteoporosis screening,
such as DEXA
bone mineral density scan,
for all women
aged 65 years and older,
and potentially starting
even earlier than 65
for women at increased risk,
such as having
a parental history
of hip fracture, being a smoker
or an excessive
alcohol consumer,
or having low body weight.
What should you do
if you're diagnosed?
Or more importantly,
what should you do
to never be diagnosed?
Before exploring
the drugs on offering
to treat osteoporosis,
there are some drugs
that may cause it,
so let's start there.
Stomach acid-blocking
"proton pump inhibitor" drugs,
so-called PPIs,
with brand names like Prilosec,
Prevacid, Nexium,
Protonix, and AcipHex,
are among the most popular drugs
in the world,
raking in
billions of dollars a year.
But then in 2006,
two observational studies
out of Europe
suggested an association between
intake of this class of drugs
and increased risk
of hip fracture,
and by 2010,
the growing evidence
forced the U.S.
Food and Drug Administration
to issue a safety alert
implicating PPI use
with fractures of the hip,
wrist, and spine.
By now, there's been
dozens such studies
involving more than
two million people
that, overall,
show higher hip fracture rates
among both long-
and short-term users
at all dose levels.
The irony is that most people
taking these drugs
shouldn't even be on them
in the first place.
These PPIs are only FDA-approved
for 10 days of use
for the treatment of H. pylori,
up to two weeks for heartburn,
up to eight weeks
for acid reflux disease,
and for two to six months
for ulcers.
Yet, in a community survey,
most users
remained on these drugs
for more than a year,
and more than 60 percent
of patients were taking them
for inappropriate reasons,
often wrongly prescribed
for "indigestion,"
for instance.
Calls to stop
this massive overuse
from regulatory authorities
have fallen on deaf doctor ears.
And now that they're available
over the counter,
the problem of overuse
may have just gotten even worse.
They can be hard to stop taking
since many patients
experience withdrawal symptoms
that can last for weeks.
In fact, if you take normal,
healthy volunteers
without any symptoms
and put them on these drugs
for two months,
and then covertly
switch them to a placebo
without their knowledge,
all of a sudden,
they can develop
acid-related symptoms,
such as heartburn
or acid regurgitation,
so ending up worse off
than they were
before they even started
taking the drugs.
In addition to bone fractures,
this class of drugs
has also been linked
to increased risk
of other possible
long-term adverse effects,
such as pneumonia,
intestinal infections,
kidney failure,
stomach cancer,
and cardiovascular disease.
In fact,
the blood vessel effects
could explain the case report
"Abrupt-Onset,
Profound Erectile Dysfunction
in a Healthy Young Man
After Initiating
Over-the-Counter Prilosec."
Oh, and also,
premature death.
There are individuals
with conditions
like Zollinger-Ellison syndrome
stricken with tumors
that can cause
excess stomach acid secretion,
for whom the risk versus benefit
of long-term use
may be acceptable,
but that's a far cry
from the 100 million PPIs
prescribed annually
in the United States alone.
To deal with acid reflux
without drugs,
recommendations include
weight loss,
smoking cessation,
avoiding fatty meals,
especially within
two to three hours of bedtime,
increased fiber consumption,
and, overall,
a more plant-based diet,
because non-vegetarianism
is associated with
twice the odds of acid reflux-
induced inflammation.
Other classes of drugs
that have been associated
with hip fracture risk
include antidepressants,
anti-Parkinson's drugs,
antipsychotics,
anti-anxiety drugs,
oral corticosteroids,
and the other major class
of heartburn drugs,
the H2 blockers, such as Pepcid,
Zantac, Tagamet, and Axid.